[Music]
so we're about two years on from the New
York Times article kind of announcing
the intellectual dialer it's right in
the center of the sort of the culture or
the national conversation those things
are always in flux and it's probably the
most kind of fast-moving part of the
culture and is is the IDW still but
going concern is it still alive is it
dead or where do you see it I mean do
you find my devotion to this ancient
religion quaint you know I would ask you
what I think the Jedi are dead right
because their temple was destroyed maybe
just a few stragglers and remnants look
people believe whatever they want to
believe I mean that doesn't really
matter
maybe it's dead maybe it's in
hibernation maybe in fact it actually
got its message out and all sorts of
people are currently carrying the
message who aren't the names that you
know because it was too easy
to pretend that Jordan Peterson wanted
in forced monogamy that sam harris was
in his llama photo that joe rogan was
some sort of a meathead right-winger
maybe the idea was that ben shapiro was
a closeted nazi who knows it's too easy
to take out individuals what I would say
is you know wherever there's someone in
danger of losing their job for making an
observation wherever there's somebody
who's trying to use their own eyes to
observe gender differences that someone
else is claiming or both there and not
there at the same time wherever you have
some situation where you need to keep a
facility open that can adjudicate
between fact and fantasy and people
don't want to be pushed into some sort
of utopian vision that isn't theirs
maybe there's a little piece of IDW
there I don't know but the key issue
isn't is it alive or dead it's what is
it and that's always been the animating
question and I would like to think that
just the way you know let's say the
weavers existed during the McCarthy era
in order to let people know that
something hadn't died completely I think
we did a pretty good job of keeping a
flame lit while the winds were blowing
at their strongest
I'd like to think that at some level
enough people are now carrying embers
from that flame that I'm a lot less
worried about this going out completely
but if you look at the run of Andrew
yang which was much better than anyone
thought could possibly he did much
better than anyone thought he could
possibly do given the amount of
institutional resistance to even
reporting his successes you'd have to
say that this has been a pretty powerful
movement I would say he would be the
quintessential sort of IDW candidate I
haven't said that before but I think
it's fair to say now it wasn't even
necessary at UVI or everything that he
wanted to do or say but he was somebody
who was coming out of the same energy
and I think it's too early to say what
the thing actually is and will be and
we're looking forward to getting Jordan
Peterson back and maybe having some
future collisions on some of these shows
and you had a really interesting
conversation with sam harris at a live
town hall event that he gave you named a
problem that i that i knew i had but i
hadn't been thinking about it i mean i
you that was you that was very useful
for here and it's now i'm worried so so
yeah well yeah so i think it is
essentially a a year in a day since the
IDW article appeared in The New York
Times which had its own weird effect on
the world and I think what we did is is
that we created a an immune reaction
where the people who had jobs as
professional commentators through
institutions realized that there was
some sort of a problem relative to their
business model and they started
attacking us with very low quality
attacks like you know when you when
you're calling ben shapiro the alt-right
something has gone wrong it's pretty
obvious I don't know whether the kippah
doesn't have the effect on them that
doesn't mean I think that we are are now
finding ourselves in a world in which
it's very hard to even understand what's
being said to us and I'm just I don't
think it's you I'm getting worse and
worse and worse
as the lousy terrible critiques that are
motivated by the political economy of a
failing business model rather than
intellectual charity and fairness and a
sense of equanimity and comity as those
attacks pile up I find that I'm just
like playing against a bad tennis player
and and my tennis game has just gone to
hell right so I have you had this
experience yeah yeah yeah well I I
didn't I yeah I knew I was I knew
something was wrong but I didn't know I
was the problem he talked about that the
from your perspective the intellectual
Darwin had created a kind of immune
reaction from the mainstream media and
the critiques have been so poor that you
felt they were actually making you worse
like a kind of poor tennis player in
your games getting worse absolutely
could you could you expand on that short
I mean the the big lazy critique is that
you just used the word all right so
there's a series of kill shots that the
commentariat attempts to use from
wherever they're positioned at the
Atlantic or Harper's or the New York
Times of the Washington put whatever
they happen to be resident and you see
this very often on Twitter and the words
are all trite thirsty grifter anybody
who's attempting to insert themselves
into a conversation which is supposed to
be gated is immediately sort of pushed
towards expulsion and all of these words
are one phrase arguments if you say that
someone is a Nazi then obviously that
person shouldn't be listened to but then
when you have to say that Ben Shapiro an
Orthodox Jew is a Nazi you do have your
work cut out for you and when you have
to say that brett weinstein is a racist
who got effectively ejected from the
University of Pennsylvania for standing
up for black women I mean at some point
you've gone completely insane and that's
where this argument really deranged is
that there have been so many bad lazy
teks by people who are trying to keep
the commentary at a guild and don't want
anyone coming in from the digital layer
I think that that's sort of the origin
of why the conversation stalls out is
that they don't want to actually
critique the ideas they don't want to
have a sit-down and and they attempt to
use the penchant for free speech as an
additional kill shot so the idea is if
they call you you know a mean white man
or something like that and then you say
I'm not gonna listen to this they say oh
I thought what about my free speech okay
well that's your argument that's the
level at which the schoolyard taunt you
know it's like I'm rubber you're glue
whatever you say bounces off me that's
the me and sticks to you that kind of
retort or no means yes yes means no do
you want me to hit you and so okay no
then you get hit yes then you get hit I
get it so I went to third grade I failed
third grade schoolyard stuff too that's
the level at which the commentary in
general attacks the ideas of others are
there any critiques that you think would
have been valuable or been useful very
few there have been a few but very few
well
it's really been pretty slim pickins
David Pakman at his best I think has
been a pretty astute and fair observer
on the harder I don't want to call it
harder left means he saw sort of weirdly
between the woke in the IDW you know
then there are people who are very smart
like for example I think of Sam cedar is
being very informed on policy terms like
he's actually following a particular
bill or you know probably knows the
names of staffers on the hill that kind
of granular detail the problem with him
is that he's got a strong trolling game
and kind of a comedic ridicule game that
is a turn-off to I mean it's okay as a
wit but it's not okay as a main course
and so I think that you could pick
through the Sam cedar stuff and find
reasonable stuff but I wouldn't
recommend it because of the reliance on
ridicule also in the conversation of sam
harris he talked about that a lot of the
criticisms of the intellect of the
members of the intellectual dark web
were made by people in the legacy media
who had kind of inherited their their
seats what are my responsibilities we've
never worked this out we've never had a
really good conversation about the fact
that the sam harris platform and the sam
harris human are very different than
than let's say the Michelle Goldberg
human on the New York Times platform and
a lot of these traditional commentators
have lower engagement as individuals and
if you think about the fusion between
the chair and the human the chair has a
lot of the power like anytime the New
York Times says that person there is
worth listening to that person whether
they have interesting ideas or not or
good or bad ideas become super important
because they inherit power from the
chair so now in that sort of set of
responsibilities comes through to me
like I don't have a book I've never show
I got nothing I just I I my wife tells
me you know I'm
your theories go to Twitter and try it
out with you with your audience you know
like that's my platform and then I hear
things like Eric you have a platform you
have a tremendous responsibility it's a
what platform I just I signed up for
Twitter and that that kind of weird new
problem is super interesting because
I've never really had to think about
this I built the entire thing completely
100% by myself you know while I'm like
doing the dishes and I'll I'll type
something and then suddenly you know
I've got a thousand people who are angry
at me or really interested in something
I've to say we haven't had the
discussion about the ethics of what if
you succeed at what it is that you're
doing on social media we and we're
inheriting these questions from people
who inherited their platforms and we
didn't in here in our platforms we built
our platforms so we've never actually
had a really good ethics discussion also
about dining ala carte there are very
few people who are so horrible that
they've never said anything remotely
interesting or reasonable I mean I
challenge you Jeffrey Dahmer or you know
Ted Bundy probably said reasonable
things you know past past the sugar
please you know not every instance of an
utterance from a bad person a horrible
person is horrible or without content
and so a lot of the criticisms were sort
of set of journalistic ethics that you
weren't you thought were were not
appropriate for some of you built that
plant in my hand absolutely well the
idea is if suddenly if you've been given
a position at let's say the Atlantic or
the New York Times your power is a
fusion between the chair in which you
sit and yourself the chair has most of
that power where you to leave that chair
would anyone even be listening to you or
how small would your audience be so when
you have that sort of a situation you
you you can talk about whether or not
somebody is abusing the power of the
chair that they have inherited even the
concept of platforming somebody I mean
this was not a verb that I was aware of
until very recently I'm sure we could do
a Google Ngram search and find out that
it's relatively recent
in origin now when somebody says well
you have a platform you have a
responsibility I think wait what
I have a youtube channel like you have a
YouTube account
I have a YouTube account well your
YouTube account is over a hundred
thousand subscribers yes but that's
because people started subscribing to my
channel it's not that you know I got a
job at Eric Weinstein YouTube channel
and then I have the responsibility of
being the custodian of this channel and
it's like screw off what the hell are
you talking about you're revealing in
essence that you and I are in different
circumstances now that's not to say I
don't have any responsibilities far from
it but to talk about well you have such
a large platform what are you going to
do it like PewDiePie well who the hell
is PewDiePie I mean PewDiePie is a guy
with the channel and whatever he did it
built an incredible followership now
does he have responsibilities yes but
really as an individual he has
responsibilities and I I do agree that
you know it's a little bit daunting that
he's got this many people listening to
him but on the other hand it's very very
different than the idea of this has been
passed to you and you must pass it to
the next person and that that this
vehicle effectively came with most of
the interest we chose you
and we gifted you this power so now with
great power comes great responsibility
that's very different than somebody who
built something with their own sweat and
people flocked to it that's the market
saying okay well I'm gonna forego all
the pleasures of listening to the
synchronized legacy stuff and I'm gonna
actually dine ala carte off the menu
because this is really interesting to me
because I come from I worked in the
newsroom Channel 4 News for 10 years i
watch the BBC of like internalized a lot
of those kind of mainstream media values
and I'm sort of seeing how they apply to
rubble wisdom and going for about 2
years and at their best I would say that
some of the values are good faith
engagement it's that you should or if
you have any other
Asians or any kind of claims to put
about someone you should put them to the
person first and get a response which
seemed like a good a good rule of thumb
that you would give space for for people
to respond and you will I mean
fact-checking should be integral to
journalism we can kind of talk about
that the mainstream media is not
actually doing a lot of the things that
it should or doing them very selectively
and saying we're gonna fact-check the
hell out of this we're going to give
this other thing a free pass I think
this is where the gonzo critique of
journalism comes in it's like would you
stop pretending to be God with a God's
eye view of the universe and don't talk
about yourself as the queen and the
first person plural for God's sakes you
know you have a perspective you have
biases you have friendships I'd rather
that you sort of tell me why I happened
to be friends with the subject so I'm
not going to necessarily throw that
person under the bus that's very funny
when you see some of these people say
well you know you gave so-and-so a free
pass like you mean my friend I gave a
free pass the person who comes over to
dinner you expect me to somehow have an
application to you to air all of my
misgivings about that person for your
viewing pleasure because of my
responsibility to the public where did
you come up with this you dear sweet
child you know I expect to be able to
tell people someone so as a friend of
mine or I you know for example my
relationship with Nassim Taleb I love
Nasim now doesn't it seem pissed me off
does he does he frighten me do I think
he's out of control when he beats up on
other people that I know and like I have
real trouble with what he's doing but do
you expect me to stab him in the back
for your pleasure because of my
commitment to some journalistic code of
ethics that no journalist is following
when I'm not a journalist I mean mmm
very funny that you've developed all
these strong feelings and beliefs and
entitlements but it is very interesting
I think I completely agree with the rise
of the alternative media has shown up
that the mainstream media has it
perspective like this kind of God's eye
view affectation is shown more and more
as an affectation like it's very obvious
well look at the mug Twitter yeah
they're the most biased completely
activist people you could imagine
pretending that you know I whenever I
get one of these people I would say can
we
over the journalistic code of ethics and
see which points because you're
violating three a paragraph two but I
would say that you've also hinted at
what some of the other failure
conditions of the new sense making
platforms are and they're very human
failings they're they're kind of
potentially audience capture they are
friendships and human human contact or
human relationships between some of the
some of the people involved can also
start to become warping of truth it
could be but one of the things that we
like to do I think is to say well so and
so is my friend I have a great deal of
private information but like you know I
don't think it's a secret that I don't
like been Shapiro's red-meat act and I
call it the red meat act that's about as
far as I want to go I don't want to
undermine Ben's ability to earn a living
or produce an entertaining news analysis
product and I've taken him to task in
public but in private when I call him up
he's about the most responsive
reasonable tolerant kind person in my
one-on-one now that is a little
uncomfortable because I don't see the
same person on the phone as the sort of
firebrand who sits behind the desk are
those two people connected they're
absolutely connected Ben and I don't
share the same perspectives on the phone
but we probably shared 90 95 percent of
the analysis and then there's like a
very extreme turn at the end but I think
that my people are much more anybody
listening to me is much better informed
about the fact that this dichotomy
between public Ben and private Ben even
exists so I would claim that you're
actually getting better information from
me than you are somebody say I would
never talk to a person like ben shapiro
because once in 2009 he said the
following thing yeah and just talking
about kind of the evolution of
journalistic ethics within the
alternative media but it seems that i
was looking at and was really interested
by was Joe Rogan's interview with Jack
Dorsey where he got this huge pushback
from his audience and then in the I
think the podcast afterwards
so just to recap for people so Jack kind
of basically stonewalled didn't give
particularly kind of complete answers
and Joe
maybe didn't didn't know enough to kind
of push back and kind of it was a as joe
said it was a kind of crappy interview
but in the next in the next interview I
think the Sam Harris he went through
that interview and was kind of like I've
got this responsibility that I never
asked for and never knew that I had I
just like talking to people and so be my
audience has given me all of this crap
for not asking Jack Daugherty to defend
sort of Twitter's banning and the way
that Twitter censors people in their
platform and companies audience really
felt like he'd let them down and what I
really respected about Joe is that you
saw him go through this process of I
never asked for this responsibility but
now I realize that I have it I'm gonna
I'm gonna do better he got Tim Poole on
for one of the future shows to have Jack
Dorsey on again but then Jack Dorsey
came on with a with the lawyer sure but
what I'm saying is that I what I feel
I'm seeing with Joe Rogan is this
evolution in real time of this is
actually and actually taking on some of
the responsibilities that he never
really asked for do you see the same way
not exactly I mean I think you know at
some point I think I got a call from Joe
or a text message I couldn't remember
and I don't want to reveal the private
contents but more or less he's kind of
like what did I just do I just said
something about Bernie and suddenly the
Bernie Sanders campaign is running you
know some sort of ad that says that
towards Tim I was like well sort of you
did in accordance with the new rules of
the world I think one of the things that
a lot of us are doing is trying to break
these expectations about do you endorse
do you condemn do you condone you know
just like would you shut up I'm a human
being
I talked to people I don't check all of
their backgrounds all the time I don't
know if they've had a tweet you know in
2011 that you know looks terrible and
then I start to learn the context and
now I find the whole history it's like
you can't move through the world if
you're saddled with all so is it great
that Joe is thinking a little bit more
about the responsibilities of being
effectively the largest show out there
yeah I think to an extent and if he
overthinks that it's gonna be terrible
because then you're not going to have an
authentic person you're gonna have the
same thing creeping in to to Joe's
thought process and will be self
censorious so I think we should take on
some amount of ethics and we should also
give ourselves a budget for ethical
failings for failures of reason for
failures of fairness and do I think the
institutions should have much lower
budgets yeah their their institutions
they're funded their long-term things
that were not usually built by any of
the people who were in them so I believe
the institutional responsibilities are
far too low and the game is - voiced
personal responsibility on to the
individuals who are outside of the
Citadel so I'm excited about the fact
that Joe wants to take on a
responsibility because I think he's a
good guy who wants to do well by the
world do I believe that he has the same
responsibilities as the New York Times
for fact-checking for you know he says
things like I voted for Gary Johnson
because he came on my show or I've met
with people and I really like Tulsi yang
and Sanders because they're not
corporate people and I'm not a corporate
comic comedian but that is the level at
which you're getting the analysis he's
speaking as a human being as human being
speak he's not speaking the way somebody
from a management consulting firm or a
PR agency would coach you to speak I
think that's very important one thing
that I like to talk about is the idea of
good faith and bad faith please because
one of the one of the things that I see
a lot in the in the news of alternative
media is some kind of gatekeeping based
on who's good faith and who's bad faith
now
it's sort of it's a paradox in a way
because you can have sort of you can
decide okay this person's bad faith it
seems to be a subjective judgment that
has always kind of laid on someone else
but I can't imagine a situation where
you say oh I'm not gonna talk to
because you're bad faith and then a few
months later they so I come back in the
way you were right actually go back then
I wasn't bad faith from now I'm in good
faith but no one like what does that
actually mean to say that someone isn't
good I think that that's quite true
David no I think some people
self-identify for examples as trolls mmm
like you meet somebody and say yeah my
troll game is strong yeah I just enjoy
dunking on people on the internet like
that that I'm using the word as they
would use the word and I'm making fun of
it I think that you know if I think
about what sam cedars perspective was on
dave rubin it was Dave Reubens a
dangerous guy and I wish to neutralize
the danger through ridicule right so I
think people will own that in many
circumstances and they'll say I'm
employing a tool for amusement for
social good and you know when it comes
to like a good faith bad faith I just
got into a really unpleasant interchange
with Yasmine Mohammed about his jobs and
she thought I was saying one thing which
I wasn't saying and so she was reacting
to that thing that she thought I was
saying and I had the sense of well these
are really unpleasant arguments you're
making back to me you're treating me
like a fool and you're treating me as
somebody with no experience no idea what
they're talking about which I didn't
think was true and so the question was
do I think I'm dealing with somebody of
good faith and I should place a call or
do I think I'm dealing with somebody
who's into a gotcha game who simply
wants to put a trophy head on her wall
and I'd had some interaction with before
I thought very highly of her so I said I
bet good faith doesn't seem like good
faith at the moment but let's stick it
out let's see what happens
sure enough takes about 20 minutes to
sort out oh that's what you're saying oh
that's what you're saying cool yeah we
called each other forget who placed the
final call that connected but the key
point is I wasn't out to get her I
wasn't out to destroy what she was
trying to say I would happily signed on
for every percentage of what she was
saying that I would agree with and as a
result I didn't think that scoring a
point on the person was a part of either
person's agenda
I think actually you can generally
ascertain not whether somebody is a good
faith person or a bad faith person but
whether that person is behaving in good
faith or bad faith towards you like for
example I've seen Michael malleus say a
lot of very intelligent things very
thoughtful things and I've also seen him
just be a dick
and so when he encountered me the other
day Twitter I was like I wonder which
Michael malice I'm gonna get and he was
just sort of being a dick I was thinking
like is this really the modality you
want to choose with me he's like yeah
let's double down okay got it that's
unfortunate because I'd seen him make
some very insightful comments I guess my
point is about good faith bad faith is
that I've seen it used like there's a
lot of conversations that are that it's
almost I've always seen it used in a way
as kind of on the on the center as a way
of sort of not engaging with certain
people rightly or wrongly it's not often
given as a reason for not engaging with
certain people that almost seems like an
inverse of the no platforming tactics on
on the Left what I've been through this
with you it's very important to exclude
people from conversation how do you know
that how do you know that those
decisions are being made now how can you
tell the difference right how can you
know that it's a good faith decision of
bad faith or good good faith declaration
of good faithful but that's just the
problem it's an issue of skill mmm you
see discernment well it's yeah this is
the dirty secret that nobody really
wants to discuss that whether or not a
society thrives or dies often can't be
written into the rules in a precise way
because everyone will read the rules and
attempt to game them oh but it says here
in paragraph 7 that if I do this that
the other thing you can't say anything
so Manion and yeah okay well that's
great so you figured out a way around
the rules you've arbitrage the letter
against the spirit now in the case of
excluding people from conversations the
key question that I usually have is is
this person attempting to be
constructive or not are they interested
in the underlying point
or are they interested in victories wins
and losses I think that a lot of people
inside of what you would call the IDW
some of them are interested
sometimes in wins and losses and you
know I've been interested in wins and
losses it's not a huge part of what I
want to be doing and in general to
somebody give you the chance you know
there are rules for fighting you smack
somebody to the curb hard and it's a
decisive victory and you think well of
your opponent you offer that person to
hand up and then you say wow I thought
you really had me if you don't do that
you're kind of a dick and I think it's
really important to understand that in
fighting if your goal is to just hang
other people's heads on your trophy wall
I would call that not good faith now
what I engage in that if I thought
somebody was a real danger and they were
just a terrible faith act or maybe but I
I think that a lot of us take a lot of
pains to not back people into corners
unnecessarily to not use gotcha
techniques to not attempt to humiliate
people to not come in guns blazing there
are all sorts of devices that kill you
off that somebody shouldn't be taken
seriously even if they're making a good
point it's like you know if there's too
much internet speak and what they're
doing too much haha like very often if I
see a lot of attempts at ridicule I just
don't even talk to the person not
because ridicule didn't previously have
a place but because there's something
about the internet where the premium on
ridicule is absolutely metastatic with
respect to what its effect on
conversation there's almost no recovery
from talking to somebody whose principle
modality is ridicule and you mentioned I
mean you mentioned Sam cedar in this
context and you taught it about in at
length with sam harris and one of your
recent podcasts yeah because it means
the sadness yeah because i think sam
cedar has a lot to offer as does michael
malice that's somebody on the left
somebody on the
and they both spend sort of a lot of
time just trying to hurt people I I feel
personally uncomfortable watching that
talking about him quite at length there
and not engaging like if that was me
being talked about by someone else I'd
feel like hang on why are you not saying
why are you not having a conversation
with me why why oh why are we not having
this conversation we don't agree on what
the rules are David I mean if you say
you know that moment when Mike Tyson bit
off somebody's ear that was awesome
because it's combat my feeling is okay I
get it so you have an idea of greater
combat you probably think that a finger
in the eye is hilarious and my feeling
is those aren't the rules of boxing that
I'm interested in so it's not that I
can't see the uf skill as a boxer it's
that you have an idea that war is war
and only you know never give a sucker an
even break and so if those are your
rules
you know why nobody wants to step in the
ring with you because you bite people's
ears off mmm would you do you not think
you could engage him and call out those
tactics I called him up we had a
perfectly reasonable conversation I
understood his perspective I think he
understood mine
I think his perspective was that
somebody like Dave Rubin in his opinion
was such a dangerous person that it was
important to stop him more or less by
any means necessary within the rules of
internet etiquette and so you know just
having an army of people constantly say
debates am cedar you coward
you know like that phrase over and over
again it's just that's his style of
attack and you know I look at that and I
say well that's not speech that I'm
interested that's not why why would
anyone I fucked her plea deal with it
nobody would mmm not if you're smart not
if you have a life
I guess it depends whether you feel that
might move on the conversation if you
were able to explain maybe it was but
the bigger issue is this sort of kind of
just nasty thing that the internet
devolves into it at the drop of a hat
it's like I have to push myself not to
become that person I don't want to be a
troll I don't want to get into gotcha
battles I don't want to
SCOR the clever little epithet you know
I mean sometimes but it's like you're
talking about a really exotic spice
being used as if it's the substrate of a
meal it's not the main course if
ridicule is the main course you're doing
it wrong and the other my other sort of
frame of the intellectual Darkover at
the beginning or my hope for it was this
sense of could this be my public
intellectuals coming together this with
very high-profile events and especially
for example take Sam Harrison Jordan
Pederson they're very famous discussions
that they had could that this sense of a
potential synthesis yeah this sense of
and I think it's Brett's Bret's line
that all true narratives must reconcile
I think he talks about that and then
this sense of for example it's sort of a
unity of knowledge point yeah so just to
give an example something like Brett's
evolutionary biology frame and Jordans
Jungian psychology frame but for me that
seems they seem to overlap because Union
psychology says we have this sort of
dark side we have kind of the killer
within us and it's like well of course
we do because we with the product of an
unbroken evolutionary chain of course
we've got the ability to kill and so
you're describing reality in different
coordinate systems there has to be a
change of coordinates yeah and my hope I
guess with the first emergence of the
intellectual dark was what was that we
might get a sense of this source of
synthesis developing yeah well I don't
think I've seen that over the last
couple of years
with plantation but with whom in other
words if you asked me yeah I would say
that Sam Harris has begun to understand
a little bit of the religious critique
that says religion may not be literally
true but it may be incredibly important
to functioning and maybe reason isn't
the only thing that globalizes and Sam
has honed his point a little bit more to
say I'm not saying religion has nothing
to offer
if you check carefully throughout time
what I've been saying is that I think
reason always has a better claim on what
you might call transcendence or
spirituality
and I think that to some extent the new
atheist conversation has kind of moved
towards one in which fitness in an
evolutionary sense and truth are seen as
competing goals at some point that they
may walk a great deal of the path
together but at some point fitness and
truth may diverge I think at our best
there has been a lot of synthesis so
that new atheism may have moved on I
would like to think that Richard Dawkins
encountering Brett was a more meaningful
conversation where there was a
recognition that maybe things don't
begin and end with random mutation or
The Selfish Gene so I think that
actually it has been happening but if
the question is what about a Superbrand
in which you've got seven to ten people
who everybody knows have conflicting
points of view progressively coming
together I mean I was there for example
you know James d'amour and Jordan
Peterson met in my kitchen I was the
organizer of the dinner where ben
shapiro and sam harris first encountered
each other in the flesh
you know brett was there when jordan
peterson met sam harris for the first
time i think that there's been a lot of
movement now if you ask me it's very
hard for this thing to have moved on
given the fact that there was no
institutional support there was just
this constant kind of tax from bad
attacks you know with like constantly
defending against whether we're all
right or white supremacist which is
every sort of beneath contempt
it's just really stupid things from
people who went to really smart colleges
defending their guild because that would
be my my follow up question which is who
has changed their minds like this set
the sensor and the framing of the
initial frame of the intellectual dark
web i think from the interview that I
did with you was these are people who
are prepared to say you've made a better
point I've changed my mind who genuinely
sort of changed them
during that during the the last two
years I think there is a widespread
sense that not that much has shifted in
terms of perspectives well let me wonder
whether that's because people are very
identified with certain perspectives
like Sam Harris with the new atheist
position I think Sam better appreciate I
think Brett's metaphoric truth position
to Sam has probably influenced Sam I
think that I better appreciate Sam's
focus on spirituality with an irrational
context I think people have better
understood why Sam doesn't believe in
free will I think that Jordans points
went from seeming a little bit fanciful
to starting to really get it some things
that I think I probably hadn't
appreciated at moved me which was that
only archetype and mythology explain why
a man would go to war that it's very
hard from an evolutionary perspective to
imagine the individuals thought process
and that it is in fact you know dreams
of glory and and the songs we sing and
that those sorts of things that propel
us into a very high probability of
self-destruction I think that you know I
was able to tell Jordan that his lobster
point isn't exactly correct because
you'd have to chase trace the serotonin
mediated hierarchy of lobsters
throughout the phylogenetic tree of
evolution and in fact you don't need
that to make your point about
hierarchies being natural but the fossil
record doesn't support it I I don't
think that that's a fair read I think
that there's been a fair amount of
movement and change when I said to Ben
Shapiro what happens if the median
individual in a society can no longer be
reached by the market and he said well
then we'd have to consider something
like socialism right like I don't think
people even hear that or what you know
and Ben and I talked about abortion we
move closer and closer to each other's
positions because we're climbing down
from the positions we've inherited from
the legacy structure so no that's not
true I mean I think there's been a lot
of movement I think what there hasn't
been is there hasn't been
just an opportunity to gather to talk
enough as friends because the key thing
that the IDW threatens is the paid
commentariat of the legacy media
structure and we talked before about how
initially at least with the framing of
the intellectual dark web that the
people who are in the article there was
a lot of because the the actual shows or
the the audiences were concentrated
around Rogan Sam Harris the Reuben
report and particularly the Reuben
report because he's based in LA that he
a lot of the initial meetings happened
there and my seller was very forward in
a lot of ways yeah did he recognize I
mean he was one of the first people to
recognize the value of the movement he
kind of got behind it he he produced a
few pieces saying announcing the
intellectual diet when I first
associated with the Reuben report and I
had an interview with Dave probably
about a year ago now we're actually and
in the run-up to that interview I
started kind of looking a little bit
more carefully about what he was doing a
night I had some serious I thought if I
have this interview with Dave there are
certain questions I have to ask him and
I was very concerned about the way that
he frames his guests I was very
concerned about whether he was actually
being truthful in in terms of the the
way that he was interviewing them and I
can understand I may not necessarily
agree with the Sam cedar perspective
that Dave Rubin is dangerous but I do
actually think that there are things
that he's doing that are yeah that can
be quite dangerous because I also see
them on Twitter for example framing
everyone who disagrees with him as bad
faith and I think that dynamic is very I
not to say the word problematic because
that's very problematic work but but i
but I do think and I've also seen like
the increased criticism of him I think
have also affected the way that people
see the intellectual dart live over the
last couple of years do you do you agree
with that do you agree that the
criticisms have taken their toll on the
way people see the intellectual dark web
because he was so identified with it
from the beginning well I think he
really embraced the potential for it and
I think
the potential for it and you know I
think that what you have to realize is I
think I made this joke about the
original title of Casablanca to get back
to that film was something like
everybody comes to Rick's or everybody
eats at Rick's I forget what it was and
I felt like well at some point everybody
came through Dave's studio because he
had built a tv-ready studio that was
truly professional and he produced an
engaging product as an engaging
interviewer and he was talking to just
about everybody who was sort of in that
digital layer and some people who were
in the legacy layer I think that what
what happened in some sense was that
when the coalescing into a thing into it
somehow you couldn't actually watch a
transition from the intellectual dark
web the loose amorphous object into the
intellectual dark web the TV channel
right or the political party or the
touring company or anything like that
because of something about this era it
just doesn't work without somebody
saying I back this with with money so
pengwern was willing to back it with
something but it wasn't like great deep
I think that what happened was that Dave
needed a business model that worked and
in so doing he was trying to pull from
all sides and eventually and you know
this is to sort of try to steal me on
his perspective I would say the
willingness of more right-of-center
elements than left-of-center elements to
tolerate discourse to tolerate people
who did not exactly line up with their
perspectives the willingness of a let's
say a Dennis Prager or a ben shapiro to
be tolerant of a gay man when they might
have strong heteronormative views was so
out of whack with what it really
expected
what the left exhibited which was this
crazy level of intolerance where if you
talked to somebody who talked to
somebody who talked to Richard Spencer
the feeling was is that what you were
clearly all right and you know those
sort of chains of association never made
sense because they were applied
completely inconsistently the fact that
Noam Chomsky talked to stefan molyneux
did not mean Noam Chomsky was tard but
somebody else talked to stefan molyneux
like Douglas Murray that person was hard
so you know there's this very confusing
set of rules as to who could talk to
whom about what under which
circumstances in gain what epithet and I
think Dave just got sick of that and
eventually said look let's let's face
facts the right is more tolerant than
the left in so doing I think he's moved
farther to the right so I think he's
become a different object now does the
intellectual darkweb tolerate movement I
do
Dave Rubin I consider a friend of mine
and I don't also don't think it's any
secret that he and I have come to
understand each other less and less well
we've been trying to have a conversation
repeatedly that never seems to close
never seems to land so I don't actually
understand exactly what's going on with
Dave nor does Dave understand what's
going on with me
now if the question is why won't you
throw Dave Rubin under a bus because you
don't understand or agree with them it's
because first of all it may be clear I'm
not in the habit of throwing my friends
under a bus for anybody else's
entertainment do I think that some of
the choices he's made are not the
choices that I would make absolutely and
I don't think it's any secret that he
feels exactly the same way about me
am i worried about some of the things
that may happen on his show yeah the way
I'm worried about some of the things
that happen on ben shapiro show
however when ben shapiro and i have a
disagreement and I call up Ben were able
to have a meeting of minds with fair
regularity I guess if you ask me I think
that the way in which Dave got hounded
was anomalous and that that created its
own feedback loop where in effect Dave
saw a world in which people were not
being fair to
and he responded accordingly saying this
is this shows the true colors of my
critics is that they're not interested
in being charitable and the people who
welcomed Dave were probably from farther
reaches of the right and they said you
can bring your wheat smoking your gay
marriage you can bring all of the things
that you value and we won't quit
criticize and judge you and so I think
he made his decision from that
perspective is that he looked at the
intolerance of the left and he looked at
the open arms coming from people farther
to the right and he said you know what
this is a better world and I'm tired of
pretending that in fact I have a better
deal from the center which pretends to
be tolerant but is anything but and at
that level I think Dave's is really
reacting the saying I refuse to have
Stockholm Syndrome
now who's responsible for that is that
Dave's fault
is that the fault of the people who
hounded him is that the fault of the
people who actually embraced the fact
that even if they didn't believe in
homosexual marriage that they wanted to
be tolerant of a fellow soul I don't
know but the problem that I have is that
I didn't I didn't and do not understand
exactly the transition that has occurred
and that's why in part I'm not super
keen to comment I don't agree with it I
don't love it but I don't also
understand it and I would be pissed off
if Dave wanted to comment on me whenever
he does comment saying that you know
he's farther in front and don't worry
that he'll bring me along I always
resented so is there some
dissatisfaction sure but there's also a
greater bond of friendship and if you
don't mind I'm gonna continue to bet on
a friend who's tried to be good to me
and who I've tried to be good to him in
return rather than necessarily this
false sense and show a performative
sense of pretending that I'm so pure
that I can't tolerate these actions from
a friend I just don't understand exactly
what's going on in the system so for me
there's a bad version of the criticisms
that are leveled of Dave Rubin which is
you platform certain people and Dave
defenses I'll talk to whoever I want to
and I think that's absolutely right
there's a more sophisticated
version of that criticism I think is
it's true and you actually have to kind
of look closely at how this happens is
how you platforming someone or how are
you what is the interaction but for me
the ethical perspective is as a someone
who comes from the mainstream media it's
like you are the position is you are
standing in for the viewer or you you
are standing in for someone else who
could be there asking me the questions
so you have a responsibility to ask the
questions that you genuinely feel should
be asked of that person who anyone any
one sort of a member of the public would
want to ask or feel should be asked and
that's an ethical decision as well
especially if you're dealing with
someone who might be very controversial
and Ruben has a lot of very
controversial people on my topic Tommy
Rob answer normally innopolis and people
like that so I do think there's a more
sophisticated version and I do think and
also maybe steel steel laning Dave
Reubens position is that he wasn't
initially he doesn't come from a
journalistic background he comes from a
comedic background and has kind of ended
up in this position but that would be
the criticism I think has got some
validity it's that he has people on his
show and then doesn't ask them the sort
of questions that would then allow the
audience to make up a complete round a
picture of that person gets defend
things they've said or whatever well
this is a different criticism and I
think it's an interesting one I think
that the key problem is that dave has a
theory and the theory is if you give
anyone enough rope they will hang
themselves and so Dave's feeling is is
that giving someone sufficient rope
allows the public to make up its mind
and the key question in that and I don't
think this is anything other than sort
of logically following from from from
that idea the key question is is there
any one skilled enough to take a large
expansive rope and never hang themselves
and I think that that would be the
weakness of that strategy for example
it's a well-known technique in the
Middle East that you say things in
Arabic that are different than the
things that you say in English and until
for example there was a group that
cropped up called memory EMRI and what
they do is they train
in Middle Eastern and languages and
Central Asian and languages potentially
into English so that you can have
everything in one language and you can
see just how much someone's speech
differs from one presentation of the
self to another and so I think that the
key thing that you'd have to say about
that is do you have people who are
incredibly skilled you brought up Tommy
Robinson look the charge has been
leveled the Tommy Robinson knows exactly
where the lines are when he's speaking
to his own troops and when he's speaking
to society at large and that he's a very
thoughtful charismatic leader who knows
the difference between the two different
postures and if you don't actually catch
him speaking to his own people you'll
never really understand what motivates
him and you know obviously that's the
problem with Dave's strategies maybe it
works for all of the people who can be
counted upon to hang themselves with
enough rope and none of the people for
whom that strategy can be evaded through
through skill so off the of the initial
constellation of people in the New York
Times article both yourself and Brett at
that point didn't have podcast you
didn't have your own kind of route to
market in a way you you both do now you
say that you've both done pretty well
out of that constellation and now kind
of launching you're launching out on
your own well I wouldn't think about it
in those terms I would say that I want
to measure I mean if the issue is
listenership yeah listenership spen
great people are incredibly motivated
but I want to measure it in terms of
actual changes in the culture and so to
the extent that we have right now people
who are working on various projects that
nobody's even aware of that are
occurring we have a very active group of
people who are discussing these issues
24/7 using let's say discord server for
voice chats
I think it's been nothing short of
amazing the level of dedication that a
lot of people have embraced these
concepts with I mean it was very weird
of course the Apple podcast showed this
is being the portal as being the number
one show in the world according to their
charts
we didn't even have a single episode out
showing that their algorithm was of
course
weirdly gheymeh bull because it
shouldn't have recorded that a podcast
with no shows was dominant so that was
it was very fun and amusing
yeah it's if you want to measure by
standard metrics of success it's been
it's been a good ride but that's not
really how we want to measure it I think
what we want to measure it by is can we
take culture to a different level that
is more rooted in reason comity
accommodation tolerance love creativity
soul transcendence than simply tearing
each other down for fun and profit and
your podcast is called the portal and
Bret's is called the dark horse yeah
what do you what are you hoping to do
with the portal is it related to what
was what the the mission of the internet
were dark levels well it's two grand and
too silly to say but the key issue is if
you think about do humans have a
thousand years left on this planet I
would guess that we do not our power is
too great in our wisdom too slight so
the key is to get people thinking well
if we want if we wish to have a future
we've always inherited a future from our
biology we've now been denied a future
by our power so if you can get people
trying to figure out if we live in
flatland how would we imagine an extra
dimension in which to escape whether
that's a dimension of thought that we've
never been able to have before a
dimension of action which we've never
undertaken or to actual actually change
the dimensions of the prison that
Einstein left us with with space and
time we've got to find a way out of our
current predicament or we don't really
have a long term future with hydrogen
devices and biological agents that can
be weaponized or digital attacks I think
it's the arms race between destruction
and protection has been lost because of
the power of the destructive objects so
we didn't know how much power there
would be within the atom or within the
cell
or within code we now know and so we've
been living on good luck for a while the
portal is an attempt to celebrate the
most creative most dynamic and most
agenting aspects of ourselves that look
for ways out when there's none to be
found
so think about Shackleton for example
and what Shackleton did when all hope
was lost was to make sure that he
brought all of his men back alive I
think it's an incredibly inspiring tale
and whenever people have been able to
find ways out where ever they thought
they were trapped they're effectively
looking for the portal that's the
purpose of the show rebel wisdom was set
up to make sense of the world at a
deeper level than the mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change which is why we want to do
what we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom gym a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching and see you soon
[Music]